<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection of certaine statutes in force, vvith full and ready notes in the margent, containing their effect in briefe. As also the ordinances for the better observation of the Lords day, and the fast dayes. Published for the better caution of such as are inclinable to delinquency against the severall effects of those statutes and ordinances. And also for the better information of all such officers and ministers as are by late speciall warrants authorised and commanded to put the same statutes and ordinances in execution. For the better suppressing 1. Of unlawfull pastimes and abuses on the Lords day.  2. Of prophane swearing and cursing.  3. Of the loathsome sin of drunkennesse.  4. Of the severall offences committed by inne-keepers, ale-house-keepers, and unlicensed ale-house-keepers.  5. Of unlawful games.  And severall other abuses. Being appointed by the Lord Mayor of the City of London to be published in all congregations within his jurisdiction.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E16_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 3:E16[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection of certaine statutes in force, vvith full and ready notes in the margent, containing their effect in briefe. As also the ordinances for the better observation of the Lords day, and the fast dayes. Published for the better caution of such as are inclinable to delinquency against the severall effects of those statutes and ordinances. And also for the better information of all such officers and ministers as are by late speciall warrants authorised and commanded to put the same statutes and ordinances in execution. For the better suppressing 1. Of unlawfull pastimes and abuses on the Lords day.  2. Of prophane swearing and cursing.  3. Of the loathsome sin of drunkennesse.  4. Of the severall offences committed by inne-keepers, ale-house-keepers, and unlicensed ale-house-keepers.  5. Of unlawful games.  And severall other abuses. Being appointed by the Lord Mayor of the City of London to be published in all congregations within his jurisdiction.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>W. B., co-author.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Robert White, and are to be sold at his house on Adling-Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLIV. [1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" signed: W.B.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Swearing --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liquor laws --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hotels --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bars (Drinking establishments) --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taverns (Inns) --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gambling --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154868:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COLLECTION Of certaine Statutes in force, VVith full and ready notes in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, containing their effect in briefe. As alſo the ORDINANCES for the better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Lords Day, and the Faſt Dayes. <hi>Publiſhed</hi> For the better caution of ſuch as are inclinable to Delinquency againſt the ſeverall effects of thoſe STATUTES and Ordinances. <hi>And alſo</hi> For the better Information of all ſuch Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as are by late ſpeciall Warrants authoriſed and commanded to put the ſame Statutes and Ordinances in execution.</p>
            <list>
               <label>For the better ſuppreſſing</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Of unlawfull Paſtimes Paſtimes and abuſes on the Lords day.</item>
                     <item>2. Of prophane Swearing and Curſing.</item>
                     <item>3. Of the loathſome ſin of Drunkenneſſe.</item>
                     <item>4. Of the ſeverall offences committed by Inne-keepers, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keepers, and unlicenſed Ale-houſe-keepers.</item>
                     <item>5. Of unlawfull Games.</item>
                     <item>And ſeverall other abuſes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>Being appointed by the Lord Mayor of the City of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, to be publiſhed in all Congregations within his Juriſdiction.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>London printed by <hi>Robert White,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe On Adling-Hill. <hi>MDCXLIV.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154868:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154868:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO The READER: To whoſe ſerious conſideration are preſented ſome Arguments to move all good Chriſtians to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Vows made in their late ſolemn Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, And accordingly to aſſiſt in this great work of active Reformation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is ſet out to thy view in this enſuing Treatiſe, ſome of the penall Statutes now in force againſt the hainous and common offences of vain ſwearing, curſing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of the Lords day, drunkenneſſe and common gaming, &amp;c. which offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have from one end of the Kingdom to the other, deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſhonoured our God, provoked his wrath againſt us, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced
<pb facs="tcp:154868:3"/> the goſpell and Religion profeſſed amongst us, and made the land to mourne and languiſh under many heavy judgements, and now at laſt under that ſore Plague of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill war: the effectuall ſuppreſsing of which abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, how happily may it conduce to repaire the honour of God, to appeaſe the wrath of the moſt high, to adorne and credit the Goſpel of Chriſt, and to obtaine healing for a bleeding, languiſhing, dying Nation.</p>
            <p>The vowes of God are upon us, moſt ſtrongly obliging us, ſincerely to aſsiſt in this worke, as appears by our late nationall Covenant for Reformation, which we have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſworne. <hi>That we ſhall ſincerely, really, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>conſtantly through the grace of God in our ſeverall places and callings, without reſpect of perſons, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſſe, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Artic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the power of godlineſſe; leaſt we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their Plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſhall alſo according to our places and callings</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Artic. 6.</note> 
               <hi>in this Common Cauſe of Religion, Liberty, and peace of the Kingdoms, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant in the maintaining and purſuing thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the forenamed ſins are ringleaders in prophanneſſe, directly oppoſite both to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe; and ſuch perſon or perſons as zealouſtie imploy themſelves by warrant from authority to ſee that the penall Statutes, and the Ordinances againſt ſuch ſins be effectually put in execution, do really proceed as by our Covenant we are ſtrictly engaged, according to our places and callings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154868:3"/>
            <p>The cruſhing of theſe outragious and moſt ſcandalous offences in this Kingdom, will be no ſmall progreſſe in the pious deſigne of Reformation, which hath been begged with ſo many prayers and tears, yea dearly bought with ſo much blood.</p>
            <p>Gods people may herein learne wiſdom of the children of this world in their generation, for when the Prelatic all and Popiſh faction had deſigned the utter ruine of the true Religion amongst us, both in truth of doctrine, and power of godlineſſe, and the introducing of Atheiſme, Popery, and prophaneſſe; their compendious method, was to ſtock up the Lords day by the roots, both by preaching, and publiſhing licentious Pamphlets againſt the doctrine, and morality of the Sabbath, and by ſending forth Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the Kings name, to be read in all Churches and Chappels, directly againſt the practicall ſanctification of the Sabbath: Whereby both all godly Miniſters, all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ordinances, and therein the whole life of Religion were expoſed to contempt; So that now we are (by Gods great bleſsing) upon the great worke of Reformation, in removing the rubbiſh of ſin, and advancing pure Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the power of godlineſſe: one moſt compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way thereto, is the carrying on of this worke in the ſuppreſsing of the aforeſaid abuſes, and that the Lords day may be reſtored to her primative glory.</p>
            <p>Much good ſucceſſe hath already crowned theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and places adjacent, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in putting a ſtop to drunken courſes, ſenſuall ſports, and other prophanations of the Lords day; which invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>London</hi> to perſiſt, and likewiſe all the Counties of the Kingdom to ſet upon the like worke, it being a worke, that doth ſo much conduce to the glory of God. And it is
<pb facs="tcp:154868:4"/> not doubted, but that the Royall City of <hi>London</hi> will be an exemplary patterne to all the Cities and Counties of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in ſpewing out, all theſe loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſins; for which the Lord might juſtly cauſe the land to vomit out her Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>The life of all our politicall Laws, conſiſts in their lively and faithfull execution, the publiſhing of theſe Statutes therefore, may be very uſefull to all, but chiefly for a rule for thoſe to walke by, that are authoriſed to put the ſame in execution; and alſo for thoſe that are ſubject to violate the ſaid Lawes, that ſo they may take warning and avoid the penalties.</p>
            <p>A happy thing it were, and much to be deſired, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a matter much conducing to the carrying on of this worke, that all godly Miniſters would informe the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the people in their preaching, of the greatneſſe of theſe offences; that ſo the ſword of the Magiſtrate, and the ſword of the Miniſtry going together, the work may be carried on with the more eaſe, to the glory of God, the credit of the Goſpel, and the comfort of the Godly. It was the practice of good King <hi>Jehoſaphat, 2 Chro. 17. 8, 9.</hi> He ſent the Prieſts and Levites to inſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in the 10. verſe ſaith the holy Ghoſt, the feare of the Lord fell upon all the Kingdoms of the lands that were round about <hi>Judah,</hi> ſo that they made no war againſt <hi>Jehoſaphat;</hi> ſuch glorious effects may this worke produce if it be done with courage for God; God now cals for men to put too their helping hand in this active worke for Reformation.</p>
            <p>And let no man think the worke too low for him, for the worke is Gods, and our Covenant binds us to it, and there is a curſe pronounced against thoſe that do it not, in
<pb facs="tcp:154868:4"/> the 48. of <hi>Jer.</hi> and the 10 verſe, <hi>Curſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently:</hi> And for our incouragement, it is ſaid in the <hi>2 Chron. 15.</hi> and the 7. verſe, <hi>Be ye ſtrong therefore, and let not your hands be weak, for your worke ſhall be rewarded:</hi> Therefore let us as the holy Ghoſt ſaith, in the <hi>1 Chron. 22.</hi> and the 16. verſe, <hi>Ariſe and be doing, and the Lord will be with us:</hi> Thus I humbly wiſh that this worke may be ſeriouſly thought upon, and faithfully car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, to the high pleaſure of Almighty God, and the profit and quiet of the Common wealth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:154868:5"/>
            <head>The Titles of the Statutes and Ordinances contained in this Collection, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Car. 1.</hi> There ſhall be no Aſſemblies for unlawfull Paſtimes on the Lords day. Page 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Car. 1.</hi> A Reſtraint of divers abuſes committed on the Lords Day. pag. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Jac. 22.</hi> The duty of Shoomakers. pag. 5.</item>
               <item>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the better obſervation of the Lords day. pag 5</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21. Jac. 20.</hi> None ſhall prophanely ſwear or curſe. pag. 9</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Jac. 9.</hi> Severall penalties of Ale-houſe-keepers, for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall offences. pag. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4. Jac. 5.</hi> The penalty of a Drunkard, and of him that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth drinking in an Ale-houſe. pag. 14.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7. Jac. 10.</hi> The penalty for an offence committed againſt any of the Branches of the Statute of <hi>1. Jac. 9.</hi> or <hi>4. Jac. 5.</hi> touching Ale-houſe-keepers and Drunkards. pag. 18.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21. Jac. 7.</hi> The Statutes of 1. Jac. 9. and 4. Jac. 5. made perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. One witneſſe ſhall be ſufficient to convince a man of Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or Drunkenneſſe. pag. 18.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Car. 4.</hi> Forreiners as well as Inhabitants ſhall not be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Tipple in Innes, Ale-houſes, &amp;c. pag. 21.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. &amp; 6. Ed. 6. cap. 25.</hi> None ſhall ſell Ale or Beer without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and they ſhall be bound by Recogniſance. pag. 22.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Car. 3.</hi> The forfeiture and puniſhment of him that keepes an Ale-houſe without Licence. pag. 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4. Jac. 4.</hi> In what caſe only Ale or Beer may be ſold to an Alc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keeper having no Licence. pag. 28.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33. Hen. 8. cap. 8.</hi> Artillery ſhall be maintained, and unlawfull Games debarred. pag. 30.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. &amp; 3. Phil. &amp; Mar. cap. 9.</hi> All Licences to keep houſes for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Games ſhall be void. pag. 35.</item>
               <item>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: for the better obſervation of the Monethly Faſt. pag. 36.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dalton, fol. 363.</hi> The Form of an Oath concerning the Office of a Conſtable. pag. 39.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154868:5"/>
            <head>Anno primo CAROLI REGIS. CAP. I. <hi>There ſhall be no Aſſemblies for unlawfull Paſtimes upon the Lords-day.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as there is nothing more acceptable to God then the true and ſincere Service and Worſhip of him, according to his holy will, and that the holy keeping of the Lords-day, is a principall part of the true Service of God, which in very many places of this Realm hath been, and now is profaned and neglected by a diſorderly ſort of people, in exerciſing and frequenting Bear-baiting, Bull-baiting, Enterludes, common Playes, and other unlawfull exerciſes and paſtimes upon the Lords-day: And for that many quarrels, bloodſheds, and other great inconveniencies have grown by the reſort and concourſe of people going out of their own Pariſhes to ſuch diſordered and unlawfull exerciſes and paſtimes, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Divine-worſhip both in their owne Pariſhes and elſewhere: Be it enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, That from and after forty dayes next after the end of this Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154868:6"/> there ſhall be no meetings, aſſemblies, or concourſe of <note place="margin">No meetings out of their own Pariſhes on the Lords day for any ſports. No unlawfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes to be uſed by any perſon within his own Pariſh. 3. 5. 4. d. for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the poor.</note> people out of their own Pariſhes on the Lords day within this Realm of England, or any the Dominions thereof, for any ſports and paſtimes whatſoever; nor any Bear-baiting, Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baiting, Enterludes, common Playes, or other unlawfull exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and paſtimes uſed by any perſon or perſons within their own Pariſhes, and that every perſon &amp; perſons offending in any the premiſes, ſhall forfeit for every offence three ſhillings four pence, The ſame to be employed and converted to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where ſuch offence ſhall be committed: And <note place="margin">A Juſtice of the County, or chief of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Town upon view, confeſſion, or proof of one witnes upon oath, ſhall give warrant to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to levie the ſaid penalty by diſtreſſe.</note> that if any one Juſtice of the Peace of the County, or the chief Officer or Officers of any City, Borough, or Town Corporate where ſuch offence ſhall be committed, upon his or their view, or conſeſſion of the party, or proof of any one or more witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by oath, which the ſaid Juſtice or chief Officer or Officers ſhall by vertue of this Act have authority to miniſter, ſhall finde any perſon offending in the premiſſes, the ſaid Juſtice or chief Officer or Officers ſhall give Warrant under his or their hand and ſeal to the Conſtables, or Church-wardens of the Patiſh or Pariſhes where ſuch offence ſhall be committed, to levie the ſaid penalty ſo to be aſſeſſed, by way of diſtreſſe, and ſale of the goods of every ſuch offender, rendring to the ſaid offenders, the over-plus of the money raiſed of the ſaid goods ſo to be ſold; <note place="margin">In default of diſtreſs the offender ſhall be ſet in the ſtocks for three hours. If any be ſued for executing this Law, he may plead the generall iſſue. None to be impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, unleſſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned within a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth after the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed.</note> And in default of ſuch diſtreſſe, that the party offending be ſet publikely in the ſtocks by the ſpace of three hours; And that if any man be ſued or impeached for the execution of this Law, he ſhall and may plead the generall Iſſue, and give the ſaid matter of Juſtification in evidence. Provided that no man be impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by this Act, except he be called in queſtion within one moneth next after the ſaid offence committed. Provided alſo, that the Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction within this Realm, or any the Dominions thereof, by vertue of this Act or any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, ſhall not be abridged, but that the Eccleſiaſticall Court may puniſh the ſaid offences, as if this Act had not been made.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154868:6"/>
            <head>Anno tertio CAROLI REGIS CAP. I. <hi>A Reſtraint of divers abuſes committed on the Lords-day.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Lords-day, commonly called Sunday, is much broken and profaned by Carriers, Wagoners, Carters, Wain-men, Butchers and Drovers of Cattell, to the great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and reproach of Religion; Be it therefore enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, &amp; the Lords &amp; Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, That no Carrier with any Horſe or Horſes, nor Waggon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <note place="margin">No Carrier with horſe, waggon-man nor Carman, with Waggons or Carts, Wain-men with Wains, nor Drover with Cattell ſhal tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell on the Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, upon forfeiture of 20. 3. for every offence. If a Butcher kill or ſell any Victuall on the Lords-day, he ſhall forfeit 6. s. 8. d. for every offence, to be levied by diſtreſs.</note> with any Waggon or Waggons, nor Car-men with any Cart or Carts, nor Wain-men with any Wain or Wains, nor Drovers with any Cattell, ſhall after fourty dayes next after the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, by themſelves, or any other, travell upon the ſaid Day, upon pain that every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons ſo offending ſhall loſe and forfeit twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for every ſuch offence: Or if any Butcher by himſelf, or any other for him, by his privity or conſent, ſhall after the end of the ſaid fourty dayes, kill, or ſell any Victuall upon the ſaid Day; That then every ſuch Butcher ſhall forfeit and loſe for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch offence, the ſumme of ſix ſhillings and eight pence; The ſaid offences, and every of them being done in view of any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace, Major, or other head Officer of any City or Town Corporate, within their limits reſpectively, or being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon Oath by two, or more witneſſes, or by the confeſſion of the party offending, before any ſuch Juſtice, Major, or head Officer, within their ſeverall limits reſpectively, wherein ſuch offence ſhall be committed; To which end every ſuch Juſtice, Major, or head Officer, ſhall have power by this Act, to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter an Oath to ſuch witneſſe or witneſſes; All which ſummes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154868:7"/> or penalties, ſhall or may be levied by any Conſtable, or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden, by warrant from any ſuch Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace, Major, or other head Officer, as aforeſaid, within their ſeverall limits, where ſuch offence ſhall be committed or done, by diſtreſſe and ſale of the offenders goods, rendring to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the over-plus; or ſhall be recovered by any perſon or perſons that will ſue for the ſame, by Bill, Plaint, or Information, in <note place="margin">
                  <p>Or to be recovered by any that will ſue by Bill, Plaint, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
                  <p>All which forfeitures ſhall be to the poor.</p>
               </note> any of his Majeſties Courts of Record, in any City, or Town Corporate, before his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, in their generall Seſſions of the Peace: All which forfeitures ſhall be employed to, and for the uſe of the poor of the Pariſhes, where the ſaid offences ſhall be committed or done, ſaving onely that it ſhall be lawfull to, and for any ſuch Juſtice, Major, or head Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, out of the ſaid forfeitures, to reward any ſuch perſon or perſons that ſhall inform, or otherwiſe proſecute any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons offending againſt this preſent Act, according to their diſcretions, ſo that ſuch reward exceed not the third part <note place="margin">
                  <p>Saving a third part to the Informer that ſhall ſue.</p>
                  <p>Which ſuit ſhall be in the County, City, or Town where the offence ſhal be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
                  <p>If Suit or Action be brought againſt any conſtable or church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden for any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres taken by them, to plead the generall iſſue.</p>
                  <p>None ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, if not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned within ſix moneths.</p>
               </note> of the forfeiture; Provided that ſuch Bill, Plaint, or Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be commenced, ſued and proſecuted in the County, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Town Corporate, where ſuch offence ſhall be committed and done, and not elſe-where, wherein no Eſſoigne, Protection or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed to the Defendant. Provided alwayes that it ſhall be lawfull for any Conſtable or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden, that ſhall have any Suit or Action brought againſt them for any diſtreſſe, by them or any of them to be taken by force of this preſent Act, to plead the generall Iſſue, and to give the ſpeciall matter in evidence: Provided likewiſe that no perſon or perſons whatſoever, ſhall be impeached by this Act, unleſſe he be thereof queſtioned within ſix moneths after the offence committed. Provided further, that this Act ſhall not in any ſort abridge or take away the authority of the Court Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154868:7"/>
            <head>Anno primo JACOBI REGIS. CAP. XXII. <hi>The duty of Shoomakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NO Cordwainer or Shoomaker ſhall ſhew, to the intent to <note place="margin">No Shomaker ſhall make, ſhew, or put to ſale, any Wares upon the Lords-day, upon pain of 3. s. 4. d. for every time, and the value of the ware beſales.</note> put to ſale any Shoes, Boots, Buskins, Startups, Slippers or Pantoſles upon the Sunday, upon pain of forfeiture for every pair of Shoes, Boots, Buskins, Startups, Slippers and Pantoſles made, ſold, ſhewed, or put to ſale, contrary to the true meaning of this Act, three ſhillings four pence, and the juſt and full value of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <head>An Ordinance of the LORDS and COMMONS aſſembled in Parliament, for the better obſervation of the LORDS-DAY.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Lords-day, notwithſtanding ſeverall good Laws heretofore made, hath been not onely greatly propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but divers ungodly Books have been publiſhed by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall Faction, againſt the morality of that Day, and to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the profanation of the ſame, to manifeſt the indangering of ſouls, prejudice of the true Religion, great diſhonour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and provocation of his juſt wrath and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt this Land; The Lords and Commons for remedy <note place="margin">All Laws enacted and in force concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords-day are to be put in due execution.</note> thereof, do Order and Ordain, and be it Ordered and Ordained, That all the Laws enacted, and in force, concerning the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lords-day, be carefully put in execution; and that all and ſingular perſon and perſons whatſoever, ſhall on every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154868:8"/> Lords-day, apply themſelves to the ſanctification of the ſame, <note place="margin">That all perſons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to the Sanctification of the Lords day both in publike and private. That no perſon cry or expoſe to ſale any goods upon forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſame.</note> by exerciſing themſelves thereon, in the duties of Piety and true Religion, publikely and privatly: And that no perſon or perſons whatſoever, ſhall publikely cry, ſhew forth, or expoſe to ſale, any Wares, Merchandizes, Fruit, Herbs, Goods or Chattels whatſoever, upon the Lords-day, or any part thereof; upon pain, that every perſon ſo offending ſhall forfeit the ſame goods ſo cried, ſhewed forth or put to ſale: And that no perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, ſhall without reaſonable cauſe for the ſame, <note place="margin">
                  <p>None to travell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forfeiture of ten ſhillings for every offence.</p>
                  <p>None to worke, or carry burthens, upon forfeiture of five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               </note> travell, carry burthens, or do any worldly labours, or work whatſover, upon that day or any part thereof; upon pain, that every one travelling contrary to the meaning of this Ordinance, ſhall forfeit for every offence, ten ſhilling of lawfull money, and that every perſon carrying any burthen, or doing any worldly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or work, contrary to the meaning hereof, ſhall forfeit five ſhillings of like money for every ſuch offence.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordained, that no perſon or perſons ſhall <note place="margin">No perſon above the age of 14. years ſhall be preſent at any ſport or paſtime whatſoever upon forfeiture of 5. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</note> hereafter upon the Lords-day, uſe, exerciſe, keep, maintaine, or be preſent at any Wreſtlings, Shooting, Bowling, Ringing of Bels for pleaſure or paſtime, Maſque, Wake, otherwiſe called Feaſts, Church-Ale, Dancing, Games, Sport or Paſtime what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; upon pain, that every perſon ſo offending, being above the age of fourteen years, ſhall loſe and forfeit ſive ſhillings for every ſuch offence.</p>
            <p>And be it further ordained, that all and ſingular perſon and <note place="margin">
                  <p>Thoſe that have the government of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren under the age of 14. years ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 12. pence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</p>
                  <p>All May-Poles to be taken down, and no more to be crected.</p>
               </note> perſons, that have the care, government, tuition or education of any childe or children, under, or within the age of fourteen years ſhall forfeit and loſe twelve pence for every of the ſaid offences that ſhall be committed by any ſuch childe and children.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the prophanation of the Lords-day hath been heretofore greatly occaſioned by May-Poles (a Heatheniſh va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, generally abuſed to ſuperſtition and wickedneſſe) The Lords and Commons do further Order and Ordain, that all and ſingular May-Poles, that are, or ſhall be erected, ſhall be taken down, and removed by the Conſtables, Borſholders, Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, petty Conſtables, and Church-Wardens of the Pariſhes and places where the ſame be; and that no May-pole ſhall be hereafter ſet up, erected, or ſuffered to be within this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154868:8"/>
            <p>And it is further Ordained, that if any of the ſaid Officers <note place="margin">The Officers for their neglect to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 5. s. for every weeke.</note> ſhall neglect to do their Office in the premiſſes, within one week after notice of this Ordinance, every of them for ſuch neglect ſhall forfeit five ſhillings of lawfull moneys, and ſo from week to week, weekly five ſhillings more afterwards, till the ſaid May-pole ſhall be taken down and removed.</p>
            <p>And that if any Juſtice of the Peace of the County, or the <note place="margin">A Juſtice of the peace of the County, Major, or chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of any corporate Town, upon view, confeſſion, or proof of one, or more wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes upon oath, ſhall give warrant to the Conſtable or Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Wardens of the Pariſh to leavy the ſaid penalties by diſtreſſe.</note> chiefe Officer or Officers, or any Juſtice of the Peace, of, or within any City, Borough, or Town-Corporate, where the ſaid offences ſhall be committed upon his or their view, or confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the party, or proofe of any one, or more witneſſes by oath (which the ſaid Juſtice, chief Officer or Officers, is by this Ordinance authorized to miniſter) ſhall finde any perſon offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the premiſſes, the ſaid Juſtice, or chief Officer or Officers, ſhall give warrant under his or their hand and ſeal, to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables or Church-wardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where ſuch offence ſhal be committed, to ſeize the ſaid goods, cried, ſhewed forth, or put to ſale as aforeſaid; and to leavie the ſaid other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures or penalties by way of diſtreſſe, and ſale of the goods of every ſuch Offender, rendring to the ſaid offenders the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus of the monies raiſed thereby; And in default of ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, or in caſe of inſufficiency, or inability of the offender to pay the ſaid forfeitures or penalties, that the party offending be ſet publikely in the Stocks by the ſpace of three hours. And all and ſingular, the forfeitures or penalties aforeſaid, ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and converted to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where the ſaid offences ſhall be committed, ſaving onely, that it ſhall and may be lawfull to, and for any ſuch Juſtice, Major, or head Officer or Officers, out of the ſaid forfeitures or penalties, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward any perſon or perſons that ſhall inform of any offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Ordinance, according to their diſcretions; ſo as ſuch <note place="margin">The Kings Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning Wakes, and recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lawfull ſports to be uſed; and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther books and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets againſt the morality of the 4. Commandment, to be burnt publikely.</note> reward exceed not the third part of the forfeiture or penalties.</p>
            <p>And it is further Ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the Kings Declaration concerning obſerving of Wakes, and uſe of exerciſe and recreation upon the Lords day; The Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Kings Majeſties Declaration to his Subjects, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lawfull ſports to be uſed;</hi> and all other Books and Pamphlets that have been, or ſhall be written, Printed or publiſhed againſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154868:9"/> the morality of the fourth Commandment, or of the Lords-day, or to countenance the prophanation thereof, be called in, ſeized and ſuppreſſed, and publiquely burnt by the Juſtices of Peace, or ſome, or one of them, or by the chief Officer or Officers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, in their ſeverall limits, or by their warrant or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Provided, and be it declared, That nothing in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <note place="margin">Meat to be dreſſed in a moderate way for preſent neceſſity.</note> ſhall extend to the prohibiting of dreſſing of meat in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families, or the dreſſing and ſale of Victuals in a moderate way in Innes, or Victualling-houſes, for the uſe of ſuch as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe cannot be provided for; or to the crying and ſelling of <note place="margin">And milk to be ſold according to the hours appointed.</note> Milk before nine of the clock in the morning, or after four of the clock in the afternoon, from the tenth of <hi>September,</hi> till the tenth of <hi>March:</hi> or before eight of the clock in the morning, or after five of the clock in the afternoon, from the tenth of <hi>March,</hi> till the tenth of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas there is great breach of the Sabbath by Rogues, Vagabonds, and Beggars, it is further Ordained, That the Lord Major of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and all Juſtices of Peace, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Church-wardens, and other Officers and Miniſters what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <note place="margin">All Laws againſt Rogues and Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds to be put in due execution, and care to be taken that they repair to ſome Church or Chappell every Sabbath-day, there to remain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine-worſhip.</note> ſhall from time to time cauſe all Laws againſt Rogues, Vagabonds and Beggars to be put in due execution; and take Order that all Rogues, Vagabonds and Beggars, do on every Sabbath-day repair to ſome Church or Chappell, and remain there ſoberly and orderly during the time of Divine worſhip, And that all and ſingular perſon and perſons, that ſhall do any thing in the execution of this Ordinance, ſhall be protected and ſaved harmleſſe by the Power and Authority of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that this Ordinance be printed and publiſhed, and read in all Pariſh Churches and Chappels, before the Sermon in the morning, on ſome Lards-day before the firſt of <hi>May</hi> next, on the South ſide of <hi>Trent,</hi> before the firſt of <hi>June</hi> next, on the North ſide of <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <head>Die Sabbathi, 6. April. 1644.</head>
                     <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Ordinance be printed and publiſhed, and read in all Churches &amp; Chappels, before the Sermon in the morning, on ſome Lords-day before <hi>May 1.</hi> next, on the South ſide of <hi>Trent;</hi> &amp; before <hi>Jun. 1.</hi> next on the North ſide of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Hen. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154868:9"/>
            <head>Anno viceſimo primo JACOBI REGIS. CAP. XX. <hi>None ſhall prophanely ſwear or curſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as all profane ſwearing &amp; curſing is forbidden by the Word of God, Be it therefore enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, that no perſon or perſons ſhall from henceforth prophanely ſwear or curſe: And that, if any perſon or perſons ſhall at any time or times hereafter offend herein, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the hearing of any Juſtice of Peace of the County, or of any Major, Juſtice of Peace, Bailiffe, or head Officer of any City, or Town Corporate, where ſuch offence is, or ſhall be committed, or ſhall thereof be convicted by the oaths of two <note place="margin">
                  <p>For every prophane oath or curſe, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender ſhall upon conviction by two witneſſes or confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, forfeit 12. d. to the poor.</p>
                  <p>The Conſtables, Ch. wardens, and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers for the poor ſhall by warrant of the Juſtice of Peace levy the ſaid forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by diſtreſſe.</p>
                  <p>In defect of diſtres, the offender (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twelve yeers of age) ſhall be ſet in the ſtocks 3. hours.</p>
                  <p>If under 12, yeers, and ſhall not forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with pay the ſaid 12. d. he ſhall be whipt by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, Parent, or Maſter.</p>
               </note> witneſſes, or by confeſſion of the party before any Juſtice of Peace of the County, or head Officer, or Juſtice of the Peace in the City or Town Corporate where ſuch offence is, or ſhall be committed; To which end, every Juſtice of Peace, and every ſuch head Officer ſhall have power by this Act to miniſter the ſame Oath: That then every ſuch offender ſhall for every time ſo offending, forfeit &amp; pay to the uſe of the poor of that Pariſh, where the ſame offence is, or ſhall be committed, the ſumme of twelve pence. And it ſhall alſo be lawfull for the Conſtable, Church-wardens, and Overſeers of the poor of that Pariſh, by warrant from ſuch juſtice of Peace, or head Officer, to levy the ſame ſumme and ſummes of money, by diſtreſſe, and ſale of the offenders goods, rendering to the party the overplus. And in defect of ſuch diſtreſſe, the offender, if he or ſhe be above the age of 12. yeers, ſhall by warrant from ſuch Juſtice of the Peace, or head Officer, be ſet in the Stocks by three whole houres; but if the offender be under the age of twelve yeers, and ſhall not forthwith pay the ſumme of twelve pence, Then he or ſhe, by warrant of ſuch Juſtice of Peace, or head Officer, ſhall be whipped by the Conſtable, or by the parent or maſter in his preſence.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154868:10"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That if any ſuch offender ſhall <note place="margin">If the offender ſue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny officer for diſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whipping, or ſtocking, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant may plead the generall iſſue.</note> commence any Suit in Law againſt any Officer or other, for ſuch diſtraining, ſale of goods, whipping, or ſetting in the ſtocks, the Defendant, or Defendants may plead the generall Iſſue, and give the ſpeciall matter in evidence to the Jury at the triall. And if it be found againſt the Plaintiffe, or that the Plaintiffe be non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, <note place="margin">And have good coſts</note> the Defendant or Defendants ſhall be allowed good Coſts, to be taxed by the Court.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheleſſe, that every offence againſt this Law, <note place="margin">
                  <p>Every offence ſhall be complained of, and proved within twenty dayes.</p>
                  <p>Thsi Act ſhall be read in every church upon the Lords-day, twice every yeer.</p>
               </note> ſhall be complained of, and proved, as aboveſaid, within twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes after the offence committed.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo enacted, That this Act ſhall be read in every Pariſh Church by the Miniſter thereof, upon the Sunday after Evening prayer, twice in the yeer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno primo JACOBI REGIS. CAP. IX. <hi>Severall Penalties of Alehouſe-keepers, for their ſeverall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas the ancient, true and principall uſe of Innes, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes <note place="margin">The true and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall uſe of Innes, Alehouſes, and other Victualling-houſes.</note> and Victualling-houſes, was for the receit, and lodging of wayfaring people travelling from place to place, and for ſuch ſupply of the wants of ſuch people as are not able by greater quantities to make their proviſion of Victuals, and not meant for entertainment and harbouring of lewd and idle peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſpend and conſume their money and their time in lewd and drunken manner:</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the authority of the ſame, that if after forty dayes next enſuing after the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, any Inne-keeper, Victualler or Ale-houſe-keeper within this Realm of England, or the Dominion of Wales, do permit or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154868:10"/> ſuffer any perſon or perſons inhabiting and dwelling in any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Town Corporate, Market Town, Village or Hamlet within this Realm of England, and Dominion of Wales, where any ſuch Inne, Ale-houſe, or Tipling-houſe, is or ſhall be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main &amp; continue drinking or tipling in the ſaid Inne, Victualling houſe, Tipling-houſe, or Ale-houſe, other then ſuch as ſhal be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited by any Traveller, &amp; ſhal accompany him during his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abode there: and other then Labouring and Handicrafts-men, in Cities and Towns Corporate, and Market Towns, upon the uſuall working dayes, for one hour at dinner time, to take their diet in an Ale-houſe: and other then Labourers and Work-men, which for the following of their work by the day or by the <note place="margin">
                  <p>If an Ale-houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſuffer a dweller of the Town or Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage where the Inne, or Ale-houſe is, to continue drinking there (but ſuch as ſhall be invited by a Traveller) he ſhall for every offence forfeit 10. s: to the poor.</p>
                  <p>Such offence being ſeen by any Major, or Juſtice, or proved by oath of two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to be taken by ſuch Major or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
                  <p>21. Jac. 7. one wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is to be taken. If he ſell leſſe then an Ale-quart of the beſt Bear or Ale for a peny, and 2. quarts of the ſmall, he ſhall forfeit 20. s. to the poor for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, proved as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove limited.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid penalties to be leyied by the Conſtables and Ch. Wardens by diſtres,</p>
               </note> great in any City, Town Corporate, Market Town or Village, ſhall for the time of their ſaid continuing in work there, ſojourn, lodge, or victuall in any Inne, Ale-houſe, or other Victualling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, other then for urgent and neceſſary occaſions, to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by two Juſtices of Peace, That then every ſuch Inne-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Victualler, or Ale-houſe-keeper, ſhall for every ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence forfeit and loſe the ſumme of ten ſhillings of currant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of England, to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where ſuch offence ſhall be committed: the ſame offence being viewed and ſeen by any Major, Bailiffe or Juſtice of Peace within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall limits, or proved by the oath of two witneſſes, to be taken before any Major, Bailiffe or any other head Officer, or any one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace, who by vertue of this Act, ſhall be authorized to miniſter the ſaid oath to any perſon or perſons that can or will juſtifie the ſame, being within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their ſaid Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any Inne-keeper, Alehouſe-keeper or Victualler, ſhal at any time utter or ſell leſſe then one full Ale quart of the beſt Beer or Ale for a peny, and of the ſmall two quarts for one peny, That then every ſuch Inne-keeper, Ale-houſe-keeper or Victualler, ſhall forfeit for every ſuch offence being duly proved in manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove limited, the ſumme of twenty ſhillings of lawfull money of England, to the uſe aboveſaid, All and every the ſaid penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be levied by the Conſtables or Churchwardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where the offence or offences ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154868:11"/> by way of diſtreſſe to be taken and detained for the ſaid forfeitures, and for default of ſatisfaction within ſix dayes next enſuring, the ſame then to be preſenlty appriſed and ſold, and the ſurpluſage or remainder over and above to be delivered to <note place="margin">And for want of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, the offender to be committed to the common gaole, till he pay the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.</note> the party, of whom the diſtreſſe was taken, and for want of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient diſtreſſe, the party or parties offending, to be by the Major, Bailiffe, other head Officer, or Juſtice or Juſtices afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, committed to the common Gaole, there to remain untill the ſaid penalty or penalties be truly paid.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if the Conſtables or Churchwardens do neglect their duty in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying, or do not levy the ſaid ſeverall penalties, or in default of diſtreſſe or diſtreſſes, from time to time, do neglect to certifie the ſame default of diſtreſſe, by the ſpace of twenty dayes then next enſuing, to the Major, Bailiffe, or other head Officer, or Juſtice of Peace within whoſe Juriſdiction the offence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: Then every perſon and perſons ſo offending, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every ſuch default, the ſumme of fourty ſhillings of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <note place="margin">If the Conſtables or churchwardens neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to levy, or to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the default of diſtreſſe by twenty dayes, they ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every default 40. s.</note> money of England, to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where ſuch offence ſhall be committed, to be levied by way of diſtreſſe of the offenders goods, by warrant from any one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace, Major, Bailiffe, or other head Officers within the limits of their Juriſdictions reſpectively, under his or their hand and ſeal, to be taken and detained for the ſaid forfeitures, for the ſpace of ſix dayes then next enſuing, Within which time if payment be not made, the ſame goods to be preſently appriſed and fold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the ſurpluſage and remainder over and above (if any be) to be delivered to the party of whom the diſtreſſe was taken: And for want of ſuch ſufficient diſtreſſe, the Conſtables, Churchwarden or Churchwardens ſo offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be by the Major, Bailiffe, or other head Officer, Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace, committed to the common Gaole, there to remain untill the ſaid penalty or penalties be truly paid: for all <note place="margin">For all which levies the Conſtables or Churchwardens ſhal be accomptable to their Succeſſors and other the Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> which penalties, which ſo ſhall be levied by the ſaid Conſtables or Churchwardens, they the ſaid Conſtables and Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, ſhall be accomptable to their ſucceſſours and other the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, in ſuch ſort as they uſually be in other Church recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or accompts. And for all forfeitures to be levied by reaſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154868:11"/> of any neglect of the Conſtables or Churchwardens, thoſe ſhall be accomptable, who by force of any Warrant or Precept do levy the ſame, or upon the enlargement of perſons committed, do receive the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That all other Laws and Statutes touching Inne-keepers, Victuallers, and Ale-houſe-keepers, ſhall ſtill remain in their former force, and be put in due execution.</p>
            <p>This Act to continue to the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parliament.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, and be it enacted by the authority of this <note place="margin">
                  <p>The puniſhment of offenders againſt this Law in either of the Univerſities, to be miniſtred by the Governours, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Juſtices of the Peace, or other principall Officers of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>And that all penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſummes of money forfeit and loſt by force of this Act within the ſaid univerſities, ſhalbe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by the Officers and Miniſters of the ſame, as ſhall he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chancellors for the time being.</p>
                  <p>And that the ſaid Governours, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and principal Officers ſhall have the like power and authority to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or otherwiſe, as in this Act is before appointed.</p>
               </note> preſent Parliament, that the correction and puniſhment of ſuch as ſhall offend againſt this Act or any part thereof within either of the two Univerſities of this Realm, or the Precincts or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the ſame, ſhall be done upon the offenders, and Juſtice ſhall be miniſtred in this behalf, according to the intent and true meaning of this Law, by the Governours, Magiſtrates, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace or other principall Officers of either of the ſame Univerſities, to whom in other caſes the adminiſtration of Juſtice, and correction, and puniſhment of offenders by the Laws of this Realm and their ſeverall Charters doth belong or appertain, and that no other within their Liberties for any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerning this Law contrary to their ſeverall Charters, do intermeddle, and that all penalties and ſummes of money to be forfeited or loſt by force of this Act, within either of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, or the Liberties or Precincts of the ſame, ſhall be levied by the Officers or Miniſters of either of the ſaid Univerſities, to be from time to time in that behalf appointed by the Vicechan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours thereof for the time being reſpectively, And that all powers and authorities either of impriſonment or otherwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given or appointed by this Act, ſhall by the Governours, Magiſtrates and principall Officers aboveſaid of either of the Univerſities, be duely executed and done within either of the ſaid Univerſities, and the Liberties and Precincts of the ſame, according to the true intent and meaning of this Act. 21. <hi>Jac.</hi> 7. <hi>made perpetuall.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:154868:12"/>
            <head>Anno quarto JACOBI REGIS. CAP. V. <hi>The Penalty of a Drunkard, and of him that continueth drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an Alehouſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas the loathſome and odious ſin of Drunkenneſſe is <note place="margin">Drunkenneſſe the root and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all other abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</note> of late grown into common uſe within this Realm, being the root and foundation of many other enormous ſins, as Bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Stabbing, Murder, Swearing, Fornication, Adultery, and ſuch like, to the great diſhonour of God, and of our Nation, the overthrow of many good Arts and munuall Trades, the diſabling of divers Workmen, and the generall impoveriſhing of many good Subjects, abuſively waſting the good creatures of God:</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the authority of the ſame, That all and every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, which after fourty dayes next following the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, ſhall be drunk, and of the ſame offence of drunkenneſſe ſhall be lawfully convicted, ſhall for every ſuch offence forfeit and loſe five ſhillings of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">Every one convicted of drunkenneſſe ſhal for every offence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 5. s. to the poor.</note> money of England, to be paid within one week next after his, her, or their conviction thereof, to the hands of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of that Pariſh where the offence ſhall be committed, who ſhall be accomptable thereof to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh. And if the ſaid perſon or perſons ſo convicted, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or neglect to pay the ſaid forfeiture as aforeſaid, then the <note place="margin">And for default of payment to be levied of the offenders goods.</note> ſame ſhall be from time to time levied of the goods of every ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo refuſing or neglecting to pay the ſame, by Warrant of Precept from the ſame Court, Judge, or Juſtices, before whom the ſame conviction ſhall be. And if the offender or offenders be not able to pay the ſumme of five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, <note place="margin">If not able to pay the ſaid, 5. s. to be committed to the ſtocks for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſix hours.</note> Then the offender or offenders ſhall be committed to the Stocks, for every offence, there to remain by the ſpace of ſix hours.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154868:12"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any Conſtable, or any other inferiour Officer of that Pariſh or place where the offence ſhall be committed, to whom that ſhall be given in charge by the Precept of any Major, Bailiffe, other head Officer, or Juſtices of the Peace within their ſeverall Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, do neglect the due correction of the ſaid offender, or the due levying of the ſaid penalties, where diſtreſſe may be had, Then every perſon ſo offending, ſhall forfeit the ſumme of ten <note place="margin">If the Conſtable neglect the due cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or levying, (where diſTres may be had) he ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 10. s. to the poor, to be levied by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe by any other perſon having war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction ſhall be.</note> ſhillings of currant money of England, to the uſe of the poor of the ſame Pariſh, or place where the offence ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to be levied by way of diſtreſſe by any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, having Warrant from any Major, Bailiffe, or other head Officer, Juſtices of Peace, or Court, where any ſuch conviction ſhall be. And to be paid to the Churchwardens as before limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who are alſo to accompt for the ſame to the uſe aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon or perſons within this Realm of England, or the Dominions of Wales, ſhall remain or continue drinking or tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in any Inne, Victualling-houſe, or Ale-houſe, being in the ſame City, Town, Village, or Hamlet, wherein the ſaid perſon or perſons (ſo remaining tiplign or drinking) doth dwell &amp; inhabit at the time of ſuch drinking and tipling, And the ſame being viewed and ſeen by any Major, or other head Officer, Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace within their ſeverall Limits, or duly proved in ſuch manner and form as is limited in and by one Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, made in the firſt Seſſion of this preſent Parliament, entituled, An Act to reſtrain the inordinate haunting and tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Innes, Ale-houſes, and other Victualling-houſes, unleſſe it be in ſuch caſe or caſes, as be tolerated or excepted in the ſaid Act, That then every perſon or perſons ſo offending, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit and loſe for every ſuch offence the ſumme of three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <note place="margin">3. 8. 4. d. for every of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of continuing drinking in an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the town or village where the party (ſo drinking) doth dwell.</note> and four pence, of currant money of England, to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where the ſaid offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, to be levied by way of diſtreſſe, in ſuch manner and form as is before appointed by this Act, for the levying of the penalty of five ſhillings for being drunk. And if it happen that any offender or offenders, againſt the true intent of this Clauſe or Branch, being thereof lawfully convicted, be not able to pay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154868:13"/> the ſaid forfeiture or forfeitures, Then it ſhall and may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any Major, Bailiffe, or other head Officer, Juſtice or Juſtices of Peace, or Court, where any ſuch conviction ſhall be, to puniſh the ſaid offender or offenders, by ſetting him, her, or them in the Stocks for every ſuch offence, by the ſpace of four hours.</p>
            <p>For the more due execution of this Statute, and for the better and more due proceeding againſt ſuch offenders, all offences of Drunkenneſſe and of exceſſe and unmeaſurable Drinking, Be it further enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, That all the offences in this Act, and in the ſaid former Act <note place="margin">All offences in this Act ſhall be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Aſſiſe, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Major, and head Officer of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City or Town Corporate.</note> mentioned, ſhall be from time to time diligently enquired of, and preſented before the Juſtices of Aſſiſes in their Circuit, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace in their Quarter or Ordinary Seſſions, and before the Majors, Bailiffs, or other head Officers of every City or Town Corporate, who have power to enquire of Treſpaſſes, Riots, Routs, Forces, and ſuch like offences, and in every Court Leet, and thereupon ſuch due proceeding ſhall be againſt the offender or offenders, for their due conviction in that behalf, as in ſuch like caſes, upon any Indictment or Preſentment is uſed by the Laws of the Realm, or Cuſtoms of the City, Town or place where ſuch Preſentment or Indictment ſhall be enquired of and found.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon or perſons being once lawfully convicted of the ſaid offence of Drunkenneſſe, ſhall after that be again lawfully convicted of the like offence of Drunkenneſſe, That then every perſon or perſons ſo ſecondly convicted of the ſaid offence of Drunkenneſſe, ſhall be bounden with two Sureties to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <note place="margin">The offender upon ſecond conviction ſhall be bound with two ſureties to be of good behaviour.</note> Lord the Kings Majeſtie, his Heirs and Succeſſors, in one Recogniſance or Obligation of ten pounds, with Condition, to be from thenceforth of good behaviour.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That all Conſtables, Churchwardens, Headboroughs, Tythingmen, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunners, <note place="margin">All Conſtabl. Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughs, Tithing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Ale-cunners, &amp; Sidemen ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Statute.</note> and Sidemen, ſhall in their ſeverall Oaths, incident to their ſeverall Offices, be charged in like ſort to preſent the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences contrary to this Statute.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That this Act or any thing therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:154868:13"/> do not in any wiſe abridge or reſtrain the Eccleſiaſticall <note place="margin">No reſtraint of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> power or Juriſdiction, but that all Ordinaries, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Judges and Officers ſhall and may proceed to enquire of, cenſure, and puniſh all ſuch offenders, according to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Laws of this Realm, in ſuch manner and form, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they lawfully might do, Any thing in this Act to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That when any of the offenders againſt the <note place="margin">There ſhall be but one puniſhment for one offence.</note> true intent of this Act, or any Branch or Article thereof, hath been once puniſhed or corrected for his or her offence, by any the ways and means before limited<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That then the ſaid offender ſhall not be eftſoons puniſhed or corrected for the ſame offence by any other ways or means.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act, or any thing therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">The Liberties of the Univerſities ſhall not be prejudiced.</note> ſhall not be prejudiciall to either of the two Univerſities of this Land, But that the Chancellour, Maſters and Scholers, and the Succeſſours of them, and either of them may as fully uſe and enjoy all their Juriſdictions, Rights, Priviledges, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as heretofore they have, or might have done: Any thing in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That no perſon or perſons ſhall be puniſhed, <note place="margin">No puniſhment if not queſtioned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſix moneths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> impeached, or moleſted for any offence mentioned in this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, unleſſe he ſhall be for the ſame offence preſented, indicted, or convicted within ſix moneths after ſuch offence committed. This Act to continue untill the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Parliament. 21. <hi>Jac.</hi> 7. made perpetuall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154868:14"/>
            <head>Anno ſeptimo JACOBI REGIS. CAP. X. <hi>The Penalty for an Offence committed againſt any of the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Statutes of</hi> 1 Jac. 9. <hi>or</hi> 4. Jac. 5. <hi>touching Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keepers and Drunkards.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas notwithſtanding all former Laws and Proviſions already made, the inordinate and extream vice of exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Drinking and Drunkenneſſe doth more and more abound, to the great offence of Almighty God, and the waſtfull deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Gods good creatures: Be it enacted by the authority of <note place="margin">The Ale-houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per upon conviction for any offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Statutes of 1. Jac. 9. or 4. Jac. 5. ſhall for 3. yeeres next after ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction be diſabled to keep any Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe. 21. Jac. 7.</note> this preſent Parliament, That if any perſon being an Ale-houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper (after ſix weeks next enſuing this preſent Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) ſhall be lawfully convicted for any offence or offences committed againſt any of the Branches of two former Acts of Parliament, made ſithence the beginning of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the one intituled, An Act to reſtrain the inordinate haunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tipling in Innes, Ale-houſes, and other Victualling-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: the other entituled, An Act againſt the odious and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſin of Drunkenneſſe, That then every perſon or perſons ſo convicted, ſhall for the ſpace of three yeers next enſuing the ſaid conviction, be utterly diſabled to keep any ſuch Ale-houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno viceſimo primo JACOBI REGIS. CAP. VII. <hi>The Statutes of</hi> 1. Jac. 9. <hi>and</hi> 4. Jac. 5. <hi>made perpetuall. One wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be ſufficient to convince a man of Tipling or Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas one Statute entituled, An Act to reſtrain the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate haunting or tipling in Innes, Ale-houſes, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154868:14"/> other Victualling-houſes, made in the firſt yeer of his Highneſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> happy raigne of England, And another Statute, intituled, An Act to repreſſe the odious and loathſome ſin of Drunkenneſſe, made in the fourth yeer of his Highneſſe raign of England, were <note place="margin">
                  <p>1. Jac. 9. &amp; 4. Jac. 5. With the alterations and additions here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after expreſſed, made perpetuall.</p>
                  <p>Where by thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes proof of 2. wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes was required. It is enacted, That one witneſſe ſhall be ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>That after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of one offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, his oath ſhall be ſufficient proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending at the ſame time.</p>
               </note> made to continue to the end of the firſt Seſſion of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and by experience have been found good and neceſſary Laws: Be it therefore enacted, That the ſaid Statutes, with the alterations and additions hereafter expreſſed, ſhall be put in due execution, and continue for ever: And whereas by the ſaid Statutes, proof of two witneſſes is required, Be it enacted, that proof of one witneſſe from henceforth ſhall be allowed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſufficient in that behalf: And that the voluntary confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (before any ſuch perſons, as by the ſaid Act are authorized to miniſter the Oath) of any perſon offending either of the ſaid Statutes, ſhall ſuffice to convince the Perſon ſo offending, after ſuch confeſſion, the oath of the party ſo offending, ſhall and may be taken, and be a ſufficient proof againſt any other offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That if any perſon or perſons, whereſoever his, or their habitation or abiding be, ſhall at any time hereafter be found upon view, or his own confeſſion, <note place="margin">He that ſtayes tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in an Inne or Alehouſe (whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he dwels) ſhal be within the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, as if he dwelt within the City or Town where the Inne or Alehouſe is.</note> or proof of one witneſſe, to be tipling in any Inne, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe, ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall be from henceforth adjudged and conſtrued to be within the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, as if he or they had inhabited and dwelt in the City, Town Corporate, Market Town, Village or Hamlet, where the ſaid Inne, Ale-houſe or Victualling-houſe is, or ſhall be, where he or they ſhall be ſo found tipling, and ſhall incurre the like pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, and the ſame to be in ſuch ſort levied and diſpoſed, as in the ſaid Act is expreſſed, concerning ſuch as there inhabit: and <note place="margin">And ſhall incur the like penalties.</note> the voluntary confeſſion of ſuch perſon or perſons ſo offending, before ſuch as by the ſaid ſtatutes are authorized to miniſter the, Oath, ſhall ſuffice to convince themſelves, and after ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, the Oath of ſuch perſon or perſons ſo confeſſing, ſhall, and may be taken by ſuch as by the ſaid Act have authority to miniſter an Oath, and ſhall be a ſufficient proof againſt any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, offending at that time.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That any Juſtice of Peace in any <note place="margin">
                  <p>That any Juſtice or Head-officer, upon his view, confeſſion of the party, or proof of one witneſſe upon oath before him, ſhal have power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any perſon of drunkennes, wherby ſuch perſon ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict ſhall forfeit 5. s. for every ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to be levied, or the offender other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe puniſhed, as in the aforeſaid Statute is appointed.</p>
                  <p>And for the ſecond offence ſha be bound to be of good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
                  <p>If any Ale-houſe keeper be convict for any offence againſt the branches of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaid two former Statutes, or againſt this Statute, he ſhalbe diſabled to keep any Ale-houſe for three years after.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154868:15"/> County, &amp; any Juſtice of Peace or other head Officer in any City, or Town Corporate, within their Limits reſpectively, ſhall from henceforth have power and authority, upon his own view, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the party, or proof of one witneſſe upon Oath before him, which he by vertue of this Act ſhall have power to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to convince any perſon of the offence of Drunkenneſſe, whereby ſuch perſon ſo convict, ſhall incurre the forfeiture of five ſhillings, for every ſuch offence, and the ſame to be levied, or the offender otherwiſe puniſhed, as in the ſaid Statute is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. And for the ſecond offence, ſhall become bound to the good behaviour, as if he had been convicted in open Seſſions, Any thing in the ſaid former Statute, made in the fourth yeer of his Majeſties raign, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That if any perſon being an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keeper, or that ſhall at any time hereafter be an Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, ſhal at any time herafter be lawfully convict for any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, againſt any the Branches of either of the ſaid two former Statutes, according to the alterations and additions therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or againſt the true meaning of this preſent Statute, That every perſon ſo convict, ſhall for the ſpace of three yeers, next enſuing the ſaid conviction, be utterly diſabled to keep any ſuch Ale-houſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the ſaid Statute, made in the fourth yeer of his ſaid Majeſties raign, intituled, An Act to repreſſe the odious <note place="margin">Conſtables, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, Head Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Tithingmen Ale-cunners, and Side-men, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and charged to preſent all offences againſt the Statute, 1 Jac. 9. and againſt the alterations and additions in this Act</note> and loathſome ſin of Drunkenneſſe, Conſtables, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Headboroughs, Tithing-men, Ale-cunners, and Sidemen, are appointed in the Oaths incident to their Offices, to be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe charged to preſent the offences contrary to the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Be it enacted, That the ſaid Oath ſhall always hereafter be alſo enlarged, &amp; extend to preſent all offences done, contrary to the ſtatute made in the firſt Seſsion of Parliament, held in the firſt yeer of his Highneſſe raign, intituled, An Act to reſtrain the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate haunting and tipling in Innes and Ale-houſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Victualling-houſes, with the alterations and additions in this Act contained, made in the ſaid fourth yeer of his ſaid Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raign according to the alterations and additions of the ſame, in this Act expreſſed, <hi>Stat. 1. Car.</hi> 4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154868:15"/>
            <head>Anno primo CAROLI REGIS. CAP. IV. <hi>Forreiners as well as Inhabitants ſhall not be permitted to tipple in Innes, Ale-houſes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas in the laſt Parliament it was enacted, That if any perſon or perſons, whereſoever his or their habitation, or abiding be, ſhould after be found, upon view or his own confeſsion, or proof of one witneſſe, to be tippling in any Inne, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe; ſuch perſon or perſons ſhould be thenceforth adjudged and conſtrued to be within the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the firſt and fourth yeers of the late Kings Majeſties raign, King <hi>James</hi> of famous memory: The one intituled, An <note place="margin">Every Alehouſe kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that ſhall ſuffer any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not dwelling in the city or town where the Ale-houſe is, to tipple in his Alehouſe contrary to the true intent of any the ſaid three Statutes, ſhall incur the ſame penalty as is appointed 1 Jac. 9. for ſuffering ſuch to tipple as dwell in the ſame City or town.</note> Act to reſtrain the inordinate haunting of tipling in Innes, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and other Victualling-houſes: And the other intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, An Act to repreſſe the odious and loathſome ſin of Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, as if he or they had inhabited and dwelled in the City, Town Corporate, Market Town, Village or Hamlet, where the Inne, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe was, or ſhould be, where he or they ſhould be ſo found tipling, ſhould incurre the like penalty, and the ſame to be in ſuch ſort levied and diſpoſed, as in the ſaid Act is expreſſed, concerning ſuch as there inhabit, but no puniſhment by any, or either of the ſaid Acts, or by any other Statute, is inflicted upon the Inne-keeper, Ale-houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or Victualler, that permits, or ſuffers ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not there inhabiting, to tipple in his Inne, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe: For remedy whereof, Be it enacted, That every Inne-keeper, Ale-houſe-keeper, and other Victualler, that at any time after the end of this Seſſion of Parliament, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and ſuffer any perſon or perſons, not inhabiting in the City, Town Corporat, Market Town, Village or Hamlet, where ſuch Inne, Ale-houſe, or Victualling-houſe is or ſhall be, to tipple in the ſaid Inne, Ale-houſe or Victualling-houſe, contrary to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154868:16"/> the true intent of any, or either of the ſaid former Statutes, the ſaid Inne-keeper, Ale-houſe keeper and Victualler ſo offending, ſhall incurre the ſame penalty, and in ſuch manner to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, levied and diſpoſed, as in the former Statute of the firſt yeer of his ſaid late Majeſties raign, is appointed for permitting ſuch to tipple as dwell in the ſame City, Town Corporate, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Town, Village or Hamlet. <note place="margin">Taverns &amp; ſuch as ſell wine, &amp; do alſo keep Inns or victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſhall be within the ſaid two former ſtatutes, and this ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That the keepers of Taverns, and ſuch as do ſell wine in their houſes, and do alſo keep Innes or Vicaualling in their houſes, ſhall be taken to be within the ſaid two former Statutes, and alſo within this Statute.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno quinto &amp; ſexto EDWARDI ſexti. CAP. XXV. <hi>None ſhall ſell Ale or Beer without Licence, and they ſhall be bound by Recogniſance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as intolerable hurts and troubles to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of this Realm, daily do grow and increaſe through ſuch abuſes and diſorders, as are had and uſed in common Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and other houſes called tipling-houſes: It is therefore enacted by the King our Soveraign Lord, with the aſſent of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, that the Juſtices of Peace within every Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty within this Realm, or two of them at the leaſt, (whereof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) ſhall have full power and authority by vertue of this Act, within every Shire, City, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or Town Corporate, Franchiſe, and Liberty where they be Juſtices of Peace, to remove, diſcharge, and put away <note place="margin">The Juſtices of Peace may diſcharge common ſelling of Ale and Beer.</note> common ſelling of Ale and Beer, in the ſaid common Ale-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and tipling houſes, in ſuch Town or Towns, and places where they ſhall think meet and convenient. And that none af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> next comming, ſhall be admitted or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154868:16"/> ſuffered to keep any common Ale-houſe, or tipling houſe, but ſuch as ſhall be thereunto admitted and allowed in the open Seſſions of the Peace, or elſe by two Juſtices of the Peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum.</hi> And that the ſaid Juſtices of the Peace, or 2. of them (whereof the one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) ſhall take bond and ſurety, from time to time, by Recogniſance <note place="margin">Recog. with ſurety by thoſe that do keep Alehouſe.</note> of ſuch as ſhall be admitted, and allowed hereafter to keep any common Ale-houſe, or tipling-houſe, as well for, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſing of unlawfull games, as alſo for the uſing and maintenance of good order and rule, to be had and uſed within the ſame, as by their diſcretion ſhall be thought neceſſary, and convenient: for making of every which Recogniſance, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Twelve pence for making the Recog.</note> or parties that ſhall be bound, ſhall pay but twelve pence.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Juſtices ſhall certifie the ſame Recogniſance at the next quarter Seſſions of the Peace, to be holden within the ſame Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe or Liberty where ſuch Alehouſe or tipling houſe ſhall be. The ſame Recog. there to remain of Record before the Juſtices of Peace of that Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe, or Liberty, upon pain of forfeiture to the King for every ſuch Recog. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and not certified, the ſumme of three pound ſix ſhillings eight pence.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That the <note place="margin">Inquiry of thoſe which have forfeited their recogniſance.</note> Juſtices of Peace of every Shire, City, Borough, Town Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Franchiſe, and Liberty, where ſuch Recogniſance ſhall be taken, ſhall have power and authority by this Act, in their quarter Seſſions of the Peace, by preſentment, information, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe by their diſcretion, to inquire of all ſuch perſons as ſhall be admitted and allowed to keep any Ale-houſe, or tipling houſe, and that be bound by Recogniſance as is aboveſaid, if they or any of them have done any Act or Acts, whereby they or any of them have forfeited the ſame Recogniſance. And the ſaid Juſtices of every Shire, and places where they be Juſtices, ſhall upon every ſuch preſentment, or information, award Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe againſt every ſuch perſon ſo preſented, or complained up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before them, to ſhew why he ſhould not forfeit his Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance, and ſhall have power and authority by this Act, to hear and to determine the ſame by all ſuch ways and means, as by their diſcretion ſhall be thought good.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:154868:17"/>
            <p>And it is further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if <note place="margin">The puniſhment of thoſe which contrary to the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Juſtices do keep Ale-houſe. 3 Car. 3.</note> any perſon or perſons, other then ſuch as ſhall be hereafter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted &amp; allowed by the ſaid Juſtices, ſhal after the ſaid firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> obſtinately, and upon his own authority take upon him or them to keep a common Ale-houſe, or tipling houſe, or ſhall contrary to the commandment of the ſaid Juſtices, or two of them, uſe commonly ſelling of Ale and Beer: that then the ſaid Juſtices of Peace, or two of them (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) ſhall for every ſuch offence, commit every ſuch perſon or perſons ſo offending to the common Gaole within the ſaid Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe, or Liberty, there to remain without bail or mainpriſe, by the ſpace of three days. And before his or their deliverance, the ſaid Juſtice ſhall take Recogniſance of him or them ſo committed, with two ſureties, that he or they ſhall not keep any common Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, tipling houſe, or uſe commonly ſelling of Ale or Beer, as by the diſcretion of the ſaid Juſtices ſhall be ſeen convenient.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Juſtices ſhall make certificate of every ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance, and offence, at the next quarter Seſſions that ſhall <note place="margin">Certificate of the Recog. and offence at the Quarter Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> be holden within the ſame Shire, City, Borough, Town Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, Franchiſe or Liberty, where the ſame ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or done. Which certificate ſhall be a ſufficient conviction in the Law, of the ſame offence. And the ſaid Juſtices of Peace upon the ſaid certificate made, ſhall in open Seſsions aſſeſſe the fine for every ſuch offence at twenty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>Provided alway, that in any ſuch Towns and places where any Fair or Fairs ſhall be kept, that for the time onely of the <note place="margin">The fine of thoſe which keep Ale-houſe without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe.</note> ſame Fair or Fairs, it ſhall be lawfull for every perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to uſe common ſelling of Ale or Beer in Booths, or other places there, for the relief of the Kings Subjects that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the ſame, in ſuch manner and ſort as hath been uſed and <note place="margin">A Proviſo for Towns where Fairs be kept.</note> done in time paſſed. This Act, or any thing therein contrary, notwithſtanding. 1. <hi>Jac. 9. 4. Jac.</hi> 4. 11. H. 7. 2. 3. Car. 3.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154868:17"/>
            <head>Anno tertio CAROLI REGIS. CAP. III. <hi>The forfeiture and puniſhment of him that keeps an Ale-houſe without Licence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas by an Act made in the fifth yeer of the reign of King <hi>Eward</hi> the ſixth of famous memory intituled, An Act for keepers of Ale-houſes to be bound by Recognizance, amongſt other things, it is enacted, That if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, other then ſuch as ſhould be from thenceforth admitted and allowed by the Juſtices mentioned in the ſaid Act, ſhould <note place="margin">Every perſon obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately keeping an Ale-houſe or Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling-houſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Juſtices to be committed to priſon for the ſpace of three dayes, there to remaine without Baile or mainpriſe. 5. &amp; 6. Exd. 6. 25.</note> after the day in the ſaid Act limitted, obſtinately, and upon his own authority, take upon him or them to keep a common Ale-houſe, or Tipling houſe, or ſhould contrary to the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Juſtices, or two of them, uſe commonly ſelling of Ale or Beer, That then the ſaid Juſtices of Peace, or two of them (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) ſhould for every ſuch offence, commit every ſuch perſon or perſons ſo offending to the common Gaole within the Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe or Liberty, there to remain without Bail or Mainpriſe, by the ſpace of three dayes: And before his or their deliverance, the ſaid Juſtices ſhould take Recogniſance of him or them ſo committed, with two Sureties that he or they ſhould not keep any common Ale-houſe, Tipling houſe, or uſe commonly ſelling of Ale or Beer, as by the diſcretion of the ſaid Juſtices ſhould ſeem convenient: And the ſaid Juſtices ſhould make Certificat of every ſuch Recognizance and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, at the next Quarter-Seſsions that ſhould be holden with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame Shire, City, Borough, Town Corporate, Franchiſe or Liberty, where the ſame ſhould be committed or done, which Certificat, ſhould be a ſufficient conviction in Law of the ſame offence: And the ſaid Juſtices of Peace, upon the ſaid Certificate made, ſhould in open Seſsions, aſſeſſe the Fine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154868:18"/> for every ſuch offence at twenty ſhillings, as by the ſaid Act may appear: Which Law hath not wrought ſuch reformation as was intended, for that the ſaid Fine of twenty ſhillings is ſeldome levyed, and for that many of the ſaid offendors, by reaſon of their poverty, are neither able to pay the ſaid Fine of twenty ſhillings, nor yet to beare their own charges of conveying them to the Gaole; and moreover, do leave a great charge of wife and children upon the Pariſhes wherein they live: In regard whereof, the Conſtables and other Officers are much diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in preſenting them, and the offenders become obſtinate and incorrigible.</p>
            <p>For remedy whereof, Be it enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, That if any perſon or perſons, after forty <note place="margin">Every one that keeps an Alehouſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Licenſe ſhall for every offence loſe 20.s to the poor.</note> dayes next enſuing the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall upon his own authority, not being thereunto law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully licenced, take upon him, her, or them, to keep a common Ale-houſe, or Tipling-houſe, or uſe commonly ſelling of Ale, Beere, Cyder, or Perry, That then every ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall for every ſuch offence forfeit and loſe the ſumme of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings of currant money of England, to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh where ſuch offence ſhall be committed; The ſame offence being viewed and ſeen by any Mayor, Bailiffe, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace, or other head Officer, within the ſeverall limits, or confeſſed by the party ſo offending, or proved by the oath of two witneſſes, to be taken before any Mayor, Bailiffe, or other head Officer, or any one or more Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace, who by vertue of this Act ſhall be authoriſed to miniſter the ſaid Oath to any perſon or perſons that can or will juſtifie the ſame, being within the limits of their ſaid Commiſſion; <note place="margin">Upon conviction the penalty is to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens for the poor by way of diſtreſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on warrant from the Mavor or Juſtice.</note> The ſaid penalty to be levyed by the Conſtables or Church-wardens of the Pariſh or Pariſhes where the ſaid offence ſhall be committed; Who ſhall be accountable therefore to the uſe of the poor of the ſaid Pariſh by way of diſtreſſe, to be taken and detained by Warrant or Precept, from the ſaid Mayor, Bailiffe, Juſtice or Juſtices, or other head Officer, by whom the ſaid offence ſhall be viewed, or before whom the ſame ſhall be confeſſed, or proved as aforeſaid: And for default of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, within three dayes next enſuing, the ſaid diſtreſſe to be by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154868:18"/> the ſaid Conſtables or Church-wardens appriſed and ſold, and the overplus to be delivered to the party or parties offending, and this to be only for the firſt offence. And if ſuch offender or <note place="margin">Through defect of diſtreſſe or not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid 20, ſhillings within ſix dayes after convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the offender to be committed to a Conſtable, or to be apprehended, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly whipped for the ſaid offence, as the Juſtice ſhall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or appoint.</note> offenders ſhall not have ſufficient goods and chattels, whereby the ſaid twenty ſhillings may be levyed by way of diſtreſſe as aforeſaid, or ſhall not pay the ſaid ſumme of twenty ſhillings, within ſix dayes after ſuch conviction as aforeſaid, That then the ſaid Mayor, Bailiffe, Juſtice or Juſtices, or other head Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, before whom the ſaid offender ſhall be convicted as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall commit all and every the ſaid offender or offenders to ſome Conſtable or Conſtables, or other inferior Officer or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, of the City, Borough, Town, Pariſh, or Hamlet, where the offence ſhall be committed, or the party apprehended, to be openly whipped for the ſaid offence, as the ſaid Juſtice or Juſtices ſhall limit or appoint.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That if any <note place="margin">If the Conſtable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect to execute his Warrant or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Gaole untill he cauſe the ſaid pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, or pay 40. s. to the uſe of the poor for his contempt.</note> Conſtable or inferior Officer ſhall neglect to execute the ſaid Precept, or Warrant, or do refuſe, or do not execute by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or ſome other to be by him appointed, upon the offender the puniſhment limited by this Statute, that in that caſe it ſhall and may be lawfull for the ſaid Mayor, Bailiffe, Juſtice or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace, or other head Officer, to commit the Conſtable, or other inferior Officer ſo refuſing, or not executing the ſaid puniſhment by himſelf, or ſome other, to the common Gaole of the ſaid County, City, or Town Corporate, there to remain without Bail or Mainpriſe, untill the ſaid offender or offenders ſhall be by the ſaid Conſtable or Conſtables, or other inferior Officer ſo refuſing, or not executing the ſaid puniſhment, or ſome by his or their procurement, puniſhed and whipped, as is above limited and declared, or untill he or they ſo neglecting or refuſing, ſhall have paid the ſumme of forty ſhillings of lawfull <note place="margin">Upon the ſecond of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and conviction of an unlicenſed ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-keeper, he or ſhe ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the houſe of correction, till by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Juſtices in their generall Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he or ſhe ſhall be freed.</note> money of England unto the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh for their ſaid contempt.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, that if the ſaid offender or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders being an unlicenced Ale-houſe-keeper, ſhall offend in any of the Premiſes the ſecond time, and be thereof lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed in manner and form aforeſaid, That then the ſaid Mayor, Bailiffe, Juſtice or Juſtices of the Peace, or other head Officer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154868:19"/> ſhall commit him, her or them unto the houſe of Correction, there to remain for the ſpace of one moneth, and be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all as idle, lewd, and diſorderly perſons. And if ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall again offend, and ſhall be thereof convicted, as aforeſaid, That then the ſaid offender or offenders for every ſuch offence, ſhall be committed unto the ſaid houſe of Correction, as aforeſaid, there to remain untill by the order of the Juſtices in their generall Seſſions for the County, City, Borough, or Franchiſe, he, ſhe, or they ſhall be delivered from thence.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that ſuch offender or offenders, as ſhall be <note place="margin">No offender having been once puniſhed either by the former Statute of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. or this Statute ſhall be puniſhed again.</note> puniſhed by vertue of this Act, ſhall not be puniſhed again for the ſame offence by the former Act, made in the fifth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth afore mentioned. And that ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or offenders as ſhall be puniſhed by vertue of the before mentioned Act, made in the fifth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, ſhall not be puniſhed again for the ſame offence, by vertue of this preſent Act, nor any thing therein contained.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that in ſuch towns and places, where any <note place="margin">That during the time of Fairs onely any perſon may ſell ale or beer.</note> Faire or Faires ſhall be kept, that for the time only of the ſame Faire or Faires, it ſhall be lawfull for every perſon or perſons to uſe common ſelling of Ale or Beer in Booths or other places there, for the relief of the Kings Subjects that ſhall repair unto the ſame, in ſuch like manner and ſort, as hath been uſed and done in times paſt, this Act or any thing therein contained to the contrary notwithſtanding. <hi>Stat. 11. H. 7. 2. 1. Jac. 9. 4. Jac. 5. 7. Jac. 10. 21. Jac. 7. 1. Car.</hi> 4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno quarto JACOBI REGIS. CAP. IV. <hi>In what caſe only Ale or Beer may be ſold to an Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper having no Licence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr the better repreſſing of Ale-houſes, whereof the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes <note place="margin">None ſhal ſell or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver Beer or Ale to any perſon that ſhall ſell it as a common tippler or Ale-houſe keeper, not having any licence then in force to ſell Ale, and Beer, upon pain of ſix ſhillings eight pence for every bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, ſo ſold or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</note> and abuſes have been and are found intollerable, and ſtil
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154868:19"/> do and are like to increaſe, Be it enacted by the Kings moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, That no perſon or perſons, by himſelf, or by any other wayes or means, directly or indirectly, ſhall at any time after three moneths next after the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament, ſell, utter, or deliver, or cauſe to be ſold, uttered, or delivered any Beer or Ale, to any perſon or perſons, or into the houſe or cellar of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, that then ſhall ſell or utter Beer or Ale, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Tipler, or Ale-houſe-keeper, the ſame perſon not having any Licenee then in force to ſell Ale or Beer, other then for the convenient uſe and expence of his, her, or their houſhold only, upon pain to forfeit for every barrell ſold, uttered or delivered contrary to the form and true meaning of this Act, the ſumme of ſix ſhillings eight pence, and ſo after that rate for a greater or leſſer quantity.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by that authority aforeſaid, That all offences to be done, or committed, contrary to the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">All offences againſt this Act ſhall be heard and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Seſſions of the peace for the County, City or Town where the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is committed by action of debt, information, Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> of this Act, and all penalties aforeſaid, ſhall be enquired of, ſued for, heard and determined in the Seſsions of the Peace for the County, City, or Borough, Town, or Liberty, or in the Court of Record of the City, Borough, Town, or Liberty, wherein ſuch offence ſhall be committed, by action of debt, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, Indictment, or Preſentment, wherein no Eſſoine, Protection, or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed to the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant: And the one half of all which forfeitures ſhall be to the uſe of the poore people inhabiting within the City, Borough, Hundred, Town, or Liberty, where ſuch offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from time to time, and the other half thereof to him or them that will ſue for the ſame.</p>
            <p>And to the end that the ſaid one half of the ſaid forfeitures above limited to be to the uſe of the ſaid poor people, may be <note place="margin">The moity of all forfeitures ſhall be to the poor, and the other half to him that will ſue for the ſame.</note> truly imployed, and beſtowed upon them, according to the true meaning of this Act, be it further enacted, That the Sheriffe, Bailiffe, or other Officer, or perſon that ſhall levy or receive any ſumme or ſummes of money forfeited and recovered according to the true meaning of this Act, ſhall and may by vertue of this Act, without further warrant, deliver the one half of the ſame
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154868:20"/> ſumme and ſummes of money, by him or them ſo levyed or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to ſome one or more of the Church-wardens and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the poore of the ſame Pariſh where the ſame offence ſhall be committed, to be by them and every of them diſtributed and beſtowed amongſt the ſaid poor people, according to the true meaning of this Act, who ſhall likewiſe have authority by vertue of this Act to diſtribute and beſtow the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That every Sheriffe, Bailiffe, and <note place="margin">The perſon that ſhal levy and receive the forfeitures by this Act, ſhall deliver half thereof to the Churchwardens and overſeers for the Poor to be by them diſtributed to the Poor. If ſuch perſon refuſe to pay over the ſaid moity, or that the Churchwardens and Overſeers do not within convenient time diſtribute the ſame to the poor, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall forfeit the double value therof.</note> other officer and perſon which ſhall levy or receive any ſuch forfeiture or forfeitures aforeſaid, and ſhall pay over the moity and one half thereof, according to the true meaning of this Act, ſhall be thereof diſcharged againſt the Kings Majeſty, his heirs and ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, That if any Sheriffe, Bayliſſe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officer or perſon ſhall refuſe to pay over the moity and one half of the ſaid mony by him or them levyed or received, or that the ſaid Church-wardens and Overſeers, to whom the ſaid mony ſhall be ſo paid, ſhall not from time to time within con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time truly diſtribute and beſtow the ſame to and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the poor people, according to the true meaning of this Act, That then every perſon ſo offending ſhall forfeit double the value thereof, to be recovered and imployed as aforeſaid.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno triceſimo tertio HENRICI octavi. CAP. IX. <hi>Artillery ſhall be maintained, and unlawfull games debarred.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BE it alſo enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that no manner <note place="margin">None ſhall keep a Common houſe, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley or place of Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Tennis, dicing table, carding, &amp;c. Upon pain to ſorfeit 40. s. for every day.</note> of perſon or perſons, of what degree, quality or condition ſoever he or they be, from the feaſt of the Nativity of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> now next comming, by himſelf, factor, deputy, ſervant or other perſon, ſhall for his or their gain, lucre, or living, keep, have, hold, occupy, exerciſe or maintain any common houſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154868:20"/> or place of bowling, coyting, cloyſhcayles, half-bowl, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, dicing table, or carding, or any other manner of game pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite by any eſtatute heretofore made, or any unlawfull new game now invented or made, or any other new unlawfull game hereafter to be invented, found, had or made, upon pain to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, and pay for every day, keeping, having or maintaining, or ſuffering any ſuch game to be had, kept, executed, played or <note place="margin">Every perſon uſing the ſaid houſes and playes, and there playing, to forfeit for every time 6. s. 8. d.</note> maintained within any ſuch houſe, garden, alley, or other place, contrary to the form and effect of this eſtatute, forty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>And alſo every perſon, uſing and haunting any of the ſaid houſes and playes, and there playing, to forfeit for every time <note place="margin">
                  <p>If any ſue for a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card, the game ſhall be contained therein that he will uſe in his houſe, and what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall play thereat.</p>
                  <p>Every placard gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the contrary to be voyd. That the party before he put ſuch Placard in execution ſhall be bound with ſureties in Chancery, not to uſe the ſaid Placard contrary to the form thereof.</p>
                  <p>That every Juſtice and headofficer may enter into all houſes &amp; places where ſuch Games ſhall be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to be holden and as well the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers as players there to arreſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon.</p>
                  <p>Untill the keepers of ſuch houſe &amp; playes have found ſureties to be bound, no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to keep or uſe ſuch houſe or playes.</p>
               </note> ſo doing, ſix ſhillings eight pence.</p>
            <p>And if any perſon hereafter ſue for any placard, to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gaming in his houſe, contrary to this eſtatute, that then it ſhall be contained in the ſame placard, what game ſhall be uſed in the ſame houſe, and what perſons ſhall play thereat, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry placard granted to the contrary, to be void: and alſo that the party obtaining any ſuch placard before he put the ſame in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, ſhall be bound with ſufficient ſureties with him by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance in the Chancery in a certain ſumme, to be appointed by the diſcretion of the Lord Chancellor of England, that hee ſhall not uſe the ſaid placard contrary to the form thereof.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that it ſhall be lawfull to all and every the Juſtices of Peace in every Shire, Mayors, Sheriffes, Bailiffes, and other head Officers, within eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry City, Town, and Borough within this Realm, from time to time, as well within liberties as without, as need and caſe ſhall require, to come, enter, and reſort into all and every houſes, places, and allies, where ſuch games ſhall be ſuſpected to be holden, exerciſed, uſed or occupied, contrary to the form of this eſtatute, and as well the keepers of the ſame, as alſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there hanting, reſorting and playing, to take, arreſt, and impriſon, and them ſo taken and arreſted, to keep in priſon unto ſuch time as the keepers and maintainers of the ſaid playes and games, have found ſureties to the Kings uſe, to be bound by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance or otherwiſe, no longer to uſe, keep, or occupy any ſuch houſe, play, game, alley or place: and alſo that the perſons there ſo found be in like caſe bound by themſelves, or elſe with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154868:21"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>And that the perſons that are ſo found, be in like caſe bound by themſelves or with ſureties by diſcretion of the Juſtices, May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, or head Officers, no more to play, haunt or exerciſe at any the ſaid places or games.</p>
                  <p>That the Maiors and head Officers ſhall ſearch weekly or once a month where any ſuch houſes or playes ſhall be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to be kept.</p>
                  <p>And if they do not ſo ſearch, to forfeit for every months ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect forty ſhillings. That no Artificer, Crafts man, hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, labourer, jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyman, Marriners, Fiſhermen, Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or any ſerving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall play at Tables, Tennis, dice Cards, Bowls, Claſh, Coyting, &amp;c. Out of Chriſtmas, under pain of 40. s. for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time.</p>
                  <p>And in Chriſtmas to play in their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſes or in their maſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
                  <p>None to play at any time at bowls, out of his garden or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, upon 6. s. 8. d. forfeiture for every time ſo offending All Juſtices, Maiors, &amp;c. finding or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhall commit them to ward, till they be bound from uſing ſuch unlawfull games.</p>
               </note> ſureties, by the diſcretion of the Juſtices, Mayors, Sheriffes, Bailiffes, or other head Officers, no more to play, haunt, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe from thenceforth, in, at, or to any of the ſaid places, or at any of the ſaid games.</p>
            <p>Alſo be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that the Mayors, Sheriffes, Bailiffes, Conſtables and other head Officers, within every City, Borough, or Town, within this Realme, where any ſuch Officers ſhall fortune to be, as well within the franchiſes, as without, ſhall make due ſearch weekly, or at the furtheſt at all times hereafter once every moneth, in all places where any ſuch houſes, allies, playes, or places ſhall be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be had, kept, and maintained. And if the ſaid Mayors, Sheriffes, Bailiffes, Conſtables, and other head Officers within their Cities, Boroughs, and Townes, as well within franchiſes as without do not make due ſearch at the furtheſt once every moneth, if the caſe ſo require, according to the tenor of this act, and do not execute the ſame in all things according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and force of the ſame: that then every ſuch Mayor, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes, Bailiffes, Conſtable, or other head Officer, to pay and forfeit for every moneth, not making ſuch ſearch, nor execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame xl. s.</p>
            <p>Be it alſo enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that no manner of artificer, or Crafts man of any handy Craft, or occupation, husbandman, apprentice, labourer, ſervant at husbandry, jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyman, or ſervant of artificer, mariners, fiſhermen, watermen, or any ſerving man, ſhall from the ſaid feaſt of the Nativity of Saint <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> play at the tables, tennis, dice, cards, bowles, claſh, coyting, logating, or any other unlawfull game, out of Chriſtmas, under the pain of xx. s. to be forfeit for every time, and in Chriſtmas to play at any of the ſaid games in their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſes, or in their Maſters preſence. And alſo that no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon ſhall at any time play at any bowle or bowles in open places out of his garden or orchard, under the pain for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time ſo offending to forfeit vi. s. viii. d. And that all Juſtices of Peace, Mayors, Bailiffes, Sheriffes, and all other head Officers, and every of them, finding or knowing any manner perſon or perſons, uſing or exerciſing any unlawfull games contrary to this preſent Statute, ſhall have full power and authority to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154868:21"/> commit every ſuch offender to Ward, there to remain without baile or mainpriſe, untill ſuch time that they ſo offending, be bounden by obligation to the Kings uſe, in ſuch ſummes of money, as by the diſcretion of the ſaid Juſtices, Maiors, Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, or other head Officers, ſhall be thought reaſonable, that they or any of them ſhall not from henceforth uſe ſuch unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games.</p>
            <p>Be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">All ſuits upon this Statute ſhal be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the year after the offence.</note> ſtatutes made for the reſtraint of unlawfull games, or for the maintenance of Artillery, as touching the penalties or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures of the ſame, ſhall be from henceforth utterly void. And all informations, plaints, actions, or ſuits that ſhall be taken or ſued upon any part of this ſtatute, ſhall be commenced within the yeer after the offence committed and done, or otherwiſe no advantage or ſuit to be taken.</p>
            <p>And where any ſuch forfeitures ſhall happen to be found <note place="margin">Where ſuch forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be in any Franchiſe or Leet, the lord to have one moity thereof, and the other to him that will ſue for the ſame in any the Kings Courts.</note> within the Precinct of any Franchiſe, Leet or Lawday, then the Lord of the ſame Franchiſe, Leet, or Lawday, to have the one moity thereof, and the other moity thereof to any of the Kings Subjects that will ſue for the ſame, in any of the Kings Courts, by action, information, bill, or otherwiſe, in which action or ſuit the Defendant ſhall not be admitted to wage his Law, nor any protection, nor eſſoine ſhall be allowed: And where ſuch forfeiture ſhall be found out of the Precinct of any Franchiſe, Leet, or Lawday, that the moity of all ſuch forfeitures ſhall be to the King our Soveraign Lord, and the other moity thereof to <note place="margin">
                  <p>And where ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture ſhal be out of any Franchiſe, the moity ſhall be to the King, and the other to him that will ſue. That all Maiors, Sheriffs, and other head Officers ſhall once every quarter make Proclamation of this Act in every Market within their juriſdictions.</p>
                  <p>That the Juſtices of Gaole delivery, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſes, and Juſtices of peace, do cauſe the ſame to be proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Circuit and Seſſions.</p>
               </note> any the Kings Subjects that will ſue for the ſame, by bill, plaint, action, information, or otherwiſe, in any of the Kings Courts, in which ſuit or action the Defendant ſhall not be admitted to wage his Law, nor any protection or eſſoine ſhall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And to the intent that every perſon may have knowledge of this Act, and avoid the danger and penalties of the ſame, be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that all Majors, Bailiffs, Sheriffs, and all other head Officers, ſhall four times in the yeer, that is to ſay, every quarter once, make open Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this preſent Act, in every market to be holden within their ſeverall juriſdictions and authorities.</p>
            <p>And alſo that the Juſtices of Gaole-delivery, Aſſiſes, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154868:22"/> of Peace, do cauſe the ſame to be Proclaimed in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall circuits and ſeſſions before them holden, and that this Statute ſhall begin to take his effect, concerning the penalties of the ſame, from the ſaid Feaſt of S. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> now next coming, and to continue and endure for ever.</p>
            <p>Provided alway, and be it enacted by the authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that if any perſon or perſons having taken by leaſe, whether it be by word, writing, or otherwiſe, any houſe, alley, or place wherein any ſuch unlawfull game now is, and at the time of ſuch leaſe made, was uſed, that then every ſuch Leſſee ſhall at the liberty of him or them, to whom ſuch leaſe is made, their executors, adminiſtrators, or aſſignes, from the ſaid Feaſt of the nativity of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> be utterly void, except it be for breach of covenants or agreements, or payment of rent due, or to be due at the ſaid Feaſt, or any time before, ſo that then at the ſame Feaſt, or within one moneth next after the ſame, the ſaid Leſſee give knowledge to ſuch Leſſor or Leſſors, their heirs and aſſignes, that he will no longer occupy the ſame, and that then it ſhall be lawfull for the inheritor, leſſor or owner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or to his heirs or aſſignes in the ſame houſe, alley, or place to re-enter.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, and be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, <note place="margin">Every Maſter may licence his ſervant to play at Cards, Dice or Tables with their maſter or other gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in his houſe, or preſence.</note> that it ſhalbe lawfull for every Maſter to licence his, or their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to play at Cards, Dice, or Tables with their ſaid Maſter or with any other Gentleman, repairing to their ſaid Maſter, openly in his or their houſe, or in his or their preſence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his or their diſcretion. And that it ſhall be lawfull to every ſuch ſervant, for every time ſo being commanded or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced by his ſaid Maſter, as is aforeſaid, to play at Cards, Dice, or Tables with his ſaid Maſter or other Gentleman, ſo to him repairing, any thing in this Act to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, and be it enacted by the authority aforeſaid, <note place="margin">
                  <p>Leaſes of houſes where unlawfull games be uſed.</p>
                  <p>The ſervant by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe may play with his Maſter.</p>
               </note> that it be lawfull to every Noble-man, and other having Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, Tenements, or other yeerly profits, for tearm of life in his own right, or in his wives right, to the yeerly value of a hundred pound, or above, to command, appoint, or licence by his or their diſcretion, his or their ſervants, or family of his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154868:22"/> or their houſe or houſes, for to play within the precinct of his or <note place="margin">In what caſes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may play at Dice, Cards, tables, Bowls or Tennis.</note> their houſes, gardens, or orchards, at Cards, Dice, Tables, Bowles or Tennis, as well amongſt themſelves as other repairing to the ſame houſe or houſes. And that they ſo playing by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appointment or licence, as is aforeſaid, ſhall not incurre any danger, or penalty contained in this Act for the ſame, this Act or any thing therein contained to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="statute">
            <head>Anno ſecundo &amp; tertio <hi>Philippi</hi> &amp; <hi>Mariae.</hi> CAP. IX. <hi>All Licences to keep houſes for unlawfull Games ſhall be void.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOſt humbly beſeecheth the Queens moſt excellent High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe your loving and obedient Subjects, the Commons in this your preſent Parliament aſſembled, that where by reaſon of divers ſundry licences heretofore granted to divers perſons, as well within the City of London, and the Suburbs of the ſame, as alſo in divers other places within your Highneſſe Realm, for the having, maintaining, and keeping of houſes, gardens and places for bowling, tennice, dicing, white and black, making and marring, and other unlawfull games prohibited by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, divers and many unlawfull <note place="margin">The inconveniences of permitting houſes for unlawfull games.</note> aſſemblies, conventicles, ſeditions, and conſpiracies, have and been daily ſecretly practiſed by idle and miſ-ruled perſons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing to ſuch places, of the which, robberies, and other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors have enſued, to the breach of your Highneſſe peace: For remedy whereof, it may pleaſe your Highneſſe, that it may be enacted by your Highneſſe, the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, that from &amp; after the Feaſt of the birth of our Lord God next coming, every licence, placard, or grant, made toany perſon or perſons, for the having, maintnance, or keeping of any bowling-allies, dicing-houſes, or other unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games, prohibited by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, ſhall be from the ſaid Feaſt utterly void, and of none effect. <note place="margin">All licences to keep ſuch houſes ſhall be void.</note> 
               <hi>Statute 33. H.</hi> 8. 9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154868:23"/>
            <head>An Ordinance of the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled: For the better obſervation of the Monethly Faſt.</head>
            <p>VVHereas the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by and with their advice and conſent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the lamentable and diſtreſſed condition of his good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> (that there might be a generall humiliation of all the eſtates of this Kingdom before Almighty God in Faſting and Prayer) was graciouſly pleaſed to command the keeping of a monethly Faſt; and to the end that all perſons might the better take notice thereof (and to leave ſuch without excuſe, as ſhould not duly keep and obſerve the ſame) did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">The Faſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be kept by the Kings Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the 8. of January 1641.</note> by his Proclamation of the 8. of <hi>January</hi> 1641. appoint that the ſame ſhould be generally, publikely, and ſolemnly hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and kept, as well by abſtinence from food, as by publike prayers, preaching, and hearing of the Word of God, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religious and holy duties, in all Cathedrals, Collegiate, and Pariſh Churches, and Chappels, within the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> (without any exception) on the laſt Wedneſday of every moneth, to continue during the troubles in the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Ireland:</hi> All which his Majeſty did ſtraitly <note place="margin">This Faſt to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue during the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Ireland on the laſt Wedneſday of every month.</note> charge and command, ſhould be reverently and devoutly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by all his Subjects as they deſire the bleſſing of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and would avoid his heavy indignation againſt this land and people; and upon pain of ſuch puniſhments as may juſtly be inſlicted upon all ſuch as ſhall contemne or neglect ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a work and duty.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Lords and Commons in both houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have received divers informations from ſeverall parts of this Kingdom and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> of the great neglect of the due obſervation and keeping of the ſaid Faſt upon the dayes appointed, and of the profanations of the ſame, by many irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligous, il-affected, looſe, and ſcandalous perſons, as well of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154868:23"/> Clergy as others, who are ſo far from afflicting their ſouls and <note place="margin">The neglect of the due obſervation of the Faſt dayes a cauſe to provoke the wrath of Almighty God againſt us. The miniſters of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pariſh to give publike notice to the people on the next Lords day before the day of Faſt, and to perſwade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to a ſolemn and religious obſervation of the whole day.</note> looſing the bands of wickedneſſe, as that they provoke the wrath of Almighty God, and make ſo pious a means to procure his bleſsings, the occaſion of greater judgements.</p>
            <p>For the prevention whereof for the time to come, the Lords and Commons do order, declare, ordaine, that in all and every the Cathedrals, Collegiate and Pariſh Churches, and Chappels within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> (without any exception) upon every Lords day next, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before any the daies appointed for the ſaid publike Faſt, the Parſon, Vicar, Curate, or Miniſter, that upon that day ſhall Officiate, or exerciſe in any of the ſaid Cathedralls, Collegiate, Pariſh Churches, or Chappels, ſhall give publike no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in every of the ſaid Cathedrals, Collegiate, Pariſh Churches, or Chappels reſpectively, of the Faſt day next enſuing, immediately after Sermon, or prayer ended in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, before the Congregation be diſmiſled, earneſtly exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and perſwading all the people to the ſolemne due keeping and religious obſervation of the whole day appointed for the <note place="margin">That all manner of ſports, and paſtimes travalling, working, and ſelling of all commodities be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne on the ſaid day. And that all Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Ale houſe kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and victuallers open not their doors nor ſell any thing but in caſes of extream neceſſity til the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like exerciſes be paſt and over.</note> ſaid Faſt, and that they would repaire to ſome Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, there diligently and reverently to attend all ſuch holy duties as ſhall be uſed in the obſervance of the ſame; that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to uſe all manner of ſports and paſtimes whatſoever, and their ordinary Trades and Callings upon the ſaid day, as well Carriers, Waggoners, Carters, Waynmen, Drovers, Butchers, Huckſters, Shop-keepers, Labourers; or any other uſing any Art, Trade, Myſtery or mannuall occupation whatſoever, and that all Vintners, Taverners, Ale houſe-keepers, and keepers of Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-houſes, do forbear to keep open their doors, Bulks, or Shops, or to ſell or utter (except in caſes of extream neceſsity) any Wine, Bear. Ale, or Victuall, till the publike exerciſes and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duties of that day in the reſpective Cathedrals, Collegiate, Pariſh Churches and Chappels be paſt and over.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, all and every the Juſtices of the Peace, Mayors, <note place="margin">That the Juſtices of the Peace, Maiors, Bayliſts, Conſtables, and Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall limits take ſpeciall notice of all perſons both mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and others that ſhall neglect or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the ſame, and returne their names &amp; offences to ſome of the Knights Citizens or Burgeſſes that ſerve for the County where ſuch offence is committed.</note> Bayliffes, Conſtables, Church-Wardens, and other Officers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting or reſiding within the limits or percincts of any ſuch Cathedrall, Collegiate, Pariſh Church, or Chappell, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required to take ſpeciall notice as well of ſuch Perſon, Vicar, Curate, or other Miniſter that ought to officiate at any of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154868:24"/> ſaid Cathedrals, Collegiate, and Pariſh Churches or Chappels, upon any ſuch day appointed for the ſaid Faſt, that ſhall either refuſe or neglect to do the ſame, or not door cauſe the ſame to be done in that religious and ſolemn manner as it ought to be, or that ſhall refuſe to give notice of the Faſt-day at the time, and in manneras aforeſaid, and forthwith to return their names, and the names of all ſuch (from time to time) as ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully offend herein, in contempt of the Lawes, his Majeſty, and both Houſes of Parliament, unto ſome one or more of the Knights, Citizens, or Burgeſſes that ſerve for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty where ſuch offence is, or ſhall be committed, that ſome ſpeedy courſe may be taken for the ſevere puniſhing of ſuch as ſhall offend herein according to the Lawes.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Die Mercurii 24 Auguſt. 1642</date>.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is this day Ordered, that this Ordinance for the better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of the Faſt be forthwith Printed and publiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <p>VVHereas the Lords and Commons in Parliament, have made an Ordinance for the more ſtrict and ſolemn kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the days of publike Faſt, which are not by all perſons duly obſerved, even in theſe times of publike Calamity, to the great diſhonour of God, and the contempt of the Authority of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Now that more particular notice may be given unto all ſuch <note place="margin">The Conſtables or their deputies ſhall the day before eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry publike faſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to every houſe within their liberty and charge all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtrictly to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame.</note> that ſhall offend herein, before any exemplary puniſhment be inflicted upon them, It is Ordered by the Commons now aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, that all Conſtables (or their Deputies) ſhall the day before every publike Faſt, repair to every houſe within their ſeverall reſpective Liberties, and charge all perſons, that they ſtrictly obſerve the Faſt, according to the directions in the ſaid Ordinance.</p>
            <p>And they ſhall upon the ſaid dayes of the publike Faſt, walk <note place="margin">And they ſhall upon the ſaid dayes ſearch diligently for all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences.</note> thorow their ſaid Liberties, diligently ſerching for, and taking notice of all perſons, who, either by following the work of their calling, or ſitting in Taverns, Victualling or Alehouſes,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154868:24"/> or any other wayes ſhall not duly obſerve the ſame, and they <note place="margin">And returne the names of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> are hereby required, to return the names of all ſuch perſons as they ſhall finde ſo offending, as alſo ſuch Informations as they ſhall receive againſt any other perſons within their Liberties guilty of the leaſt offence, unto the Committee for Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſo they may be proceeded againſt for the contempt of the ſaid Ordinance; And all Conſtables are to obſerve theſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections from time to time, ſo long as the ſaid publike Faſt ſhall be kept, without expecting any further Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <head>The Form of an Oath concerning the Office of a Conſtable.</head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſwear, that you ſhall well and truly ſerve our <note place="margin">Dalton, fol. 363.</note> Soveraign Lord the King in the Office of a Conſtable: you ſhall ſee and cauſe his Majeſties Peace to be well and duly kept and preſerved according to your power: you ſhall arreſt all ſuch perſons, as in your ſight and preſence ſhall ride or go armed offenſively, or ſhall commit or make any Riot, Affray, or other breach of his Majeſties Peace: you ſhall do your beſt indeavour (upon complaint to you made) to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all Felons, Barrettors, and Riotors, or perſons riotouſly aſſembled: and if any ſuch Offender ſhall make reſiſtance (with force) you ſhall levie Huy and Cry, and ſhall purſue them untill they be taken: you ſhall do your beſt indeavour that the Watch in and about your Town be duly kept for the apprehending of Rogues, Vagabonds, Night-walkers, Eveſdroppers, Scouts, ſuch as go armed, and the like; and that Huy and Cries be duly raiſed and purſued according to the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Murtherers, Theeves, and other Felons. And that the Statutes made for the puniſhment of Rogues and Vagabonds, and ſuch other idle perſons, coming within your Bounds and Limits, be duly put in execution: you ſhall have a watchfull eye to ſuch perſons as ſhall maintain or keep any common houſe or place where any unlawfull game is or ſhall be uſed; as alſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154868:25"/> to ſuch as ſhall frequent or uſe ſuch places, or ſhall uſe or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any unlawfull games there, or elſewhere contrary to the Statutes. At your Aſſiſes, Seſſions of the Peace, or Leet, you ſhall preſent all and every the offences done, contrary to the Statutes made (1. <hi>Jacobi, 4. Jacobi, &amp; 21. Jacobi Regis</hi>) to reſtrain the inordinate hanting or tippling in Innes, Alehouſes, and other Victualling houſes, and for repreſſing of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: you ſhall there likewiſe true preſentment make of all Blood-ſheddings, Affrays, Out-cries, Reſcous, and other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed or done againſt the Kings Majeſties Peace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Limits: and you ſhall have a care for the maintenance of Archerie according to the Statute: you ſhall well and duly execute all Precepts and Warrants to you directed from the Juſtices of Peace of this County: And you ſhall well and duly according to your knowledge, power, and ability, do and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all other things belonging to the Office of a Conſtable, ſo long as you ſhall continue in this Office. So help you God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
